Helen Ashurst Choate Papers, 1908-1957
Smith College Archives
Helen Ashurst Choate Papers
1817-1957
Choate, Helen Ashurst
RG 42 UUID:15deb979-55cb-4beb-bafc-da65deb59b2c
1 box (.4 linear ft.)
Smith College Archives Northampton, MA
Professor of Botany. Contains biographical information, correspondence, clippings, notes, and publications.
Smith College Teaching Fellow, 1908-1909
Associate Professor of Botany, 1909-1947
Class Dean for the Class of 1938, 1934-1938
Associate Professor Emeritus, 1947-1957
Helen Ashurst Choate was born on August 29, 1882 in Irvington-on-Hudson, NY to Washington Choate and Grace Whitton Choate. She graduated from Smith College with the Class of 1904, and worked as a teacher at Greenwich Academy in Connecticut before returning to Smith on a trustee fellowship from 1908-1909. In 1909, studying under professor William F. Ganong, Choate received an M.A. from Smith and became an associate professor of botany, a position she held for 38 years until her retirement in 1947. In 1920, she received a Ph.D. from the University of Chicago. Between 1934-1938 she served as Class Dean for the Class of 1938, and she also served as department chair for several years. Her field of research was plant physiology.
Choate was active with the work of the Edwards Congregational Church in Northampton, hospital aid, victory gardens, the Red Cross, and relief work. She was also a member of Phi Beta Kappa, Sigma Xi, and Sigma Delta Epsilon, the American Association for the Advancement of Science, the Botanical Society of America, and the History of Science Society.
Choate died at the age of 75 on December 12, 1957 at Cooley Dickinson Hospital in Northampton, MA.
The Helen Ashurst Choate collection contains biographical information, including photographs and obituaries, correspondence, news clippings, notes, documents relating to book making, bibliographies, and publications.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives without any additional restrictions.
Additional Information
Related Material
52. Department of Botany Records
80. Class of 1904 Records
- Biographical Information 1889-1997 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence: A-Z 1903-1950 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence: Clarke, Elizabeth Lawrence (1883) 1950 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence: Cutler, Anna Alice (1885) 1950 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence: Jones, Grace (Smith) (1894) 1950 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence: Pillsbury, John H. undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Autographed letters from botanists 1908-1918 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Bibliography undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Clippings from book dealer's catalogue undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Early American botanists 1912, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Familiar Lectures on Botany 1829 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Herbals (Botany 11) undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Herbs undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- History of botany (Botany 41) 1931, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- History of botany: early herbals undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- History of botany: notes 1910, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
- History of botany: timeline undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
- "History of the Botany Department": Draft c.a. 1950s (Box 1, Folder 18)
- "History of the Botany Department": Final Copy c.a. 1950s (Box 1, Folder 19)
- "History of the Botany Department": Notes 1940-1953, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
- "John Gerard: 1545-1612" 1925-1943 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- "Invention of Printing and Early Printed Books" undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
- "Journal of Hellenic Studies" 1927 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Kurt Sprengel's History of Botany 1817 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Lecture notes: A-H undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Magazine clippings and publication information 1915-1918, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Materials on Linnaeus and publications by the Linnean Society of London 1908-1930, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Plant reproduction clippings undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Pre-Aristotelian botany 1913, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Thornton College notes undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Theophrastus: Enquiry into Plants undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Science of botany: notes undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
- "Scientific Monthly" clippings 1928-1934 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Woodcut book materials and articles 1931, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Miscellaneous and clippings undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Miscellaneous 1 & 2 undated (Box 1, Folder 36-37)
- Miscellaneous publications and bibliographies 1920-1932 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Publications by Choate 1912-1940 (Box 1, Folder 39)